{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One of this ruler’s sons was murdered in the arms of this ruler’s wife, Julia Domna. This emperor died in Eboracum while campaigning in Scotland. At the second century Battle of Issus, this leader defeated one of his rivals, Pescennius [pesk-EHN-ee-uss] Niger. This man emerged victorious from the Year of the Five Emperors. His son Geta was killed by his other son and successor Caracalla. For 10 points, identify this Roman emperor from 193 to 211 and founder of the Severan dynasty.",
      "answer": "Septimius Severus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This singer quoted Khrushchev’s line “We will bury you!” and hoped the title people “love their children too” in his song “Russians”. He performed alongside Branford Marsalis and Phil Collins at Live Aid in 1985. More famously, he joined Andy Summers and Stewart Copeland in a band for which he sang a song inspired by Nabokov’s Lolita called “Don’t Stand So Close To Me.” For 10 points, name this man who wrote “Message in a Bottle” for the band in which he was lead singer, The Police.",
      "answer": "Sting"
    },
    {
      "question": "Participants in this uprising gathered at Braddock’s Field and Parkinson's Ferry. It began when members of a local “Democratic Society” burned John Neville’s home. This rebellion was sparked by an excise tax levied by Alexander Hamilton, and put down by a militia led by Virginia governor “Light-Horse Harry” Lee and President George Washington. For 10 points, name this 1794 rebellion in Pennsylvania named for an alcoholic beverage.",
      "answer": "Whiskey Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "The death of Mary appears in the middle of one of these works in Poland by Veit Stoss [VAYT stohs]. Saint Margaret holds a book and stands on top of a dragon on the right side one of these works by Hugo van der Goes. Saint Cecilia plays the organ in one of these works featuring an enthroned figure flanked by John the Baptist and Mary, which was commissioned by the artist's brother Hubert. For 10 points, name these works of art, one of which was painted by Jan Van Eyck and named for Ghent.",
      "answer": "altarpieces"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person was appointed to an Industrial Commission by then-Governor Al Smith and served as head of the New York Consumer's League. This person was succeeded by Lewis Schwellenbach after spending a record length of time in that role. Her accomplishments include founding the precursor to OSHA, chairing the 1935 Committee on Economic Security and fighting for legislation to regulate wages and hours for employees. For 10 points, name this Secretary of Labor under FDR, the first female cabinet member.",
      "answer": "Frances Perkins"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person first came to power under the tutelage of Concino Concini, who was killed due to the influence of Charles de Luynes. He led the attempt to capture La Rochelle, making Huguenots sign the Peace of Alais. He was the target of the Day of the Dupes, when Marie de Medici attempted to have him removed. He led the French cause in the Thirty Years War and was replaced by Mazarin after his death. For 10 points, name this cardinal who advised Louis XIII.",
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu"
    },
    {
      "question": "An effect named for this scientist concerns the rotation of the plane of polarization of light in matter upon the application of magnetic field. His motor used a magnetic field to rotate a current-carrying wire resting on a pool of mercury. An object enclosed by a conductor is unperturbed by external electric fields, and hence rests in a cage named for this man. For 10 points, name this physicist, who started his career as an apprentice to Humphry Davy and discovered a law of electromagnetic induction.",
      "answer": "Michael Faraday"
    },
    {
      "question": "A philosopher from this country contended that reality had been replaced entirely by symbols and signs in the book Simulacra and Simulation. Jurgen Habermas discussed the 9/11 attacks in a series of dialogues on terrorism with a philosopher from this country. That philosopher from this country described ten \"plagues\" of capitalism in Specters of Marx and discussed différance in the book Of Grammatology. For 10 points, name this country where deconstructionism was founded by Jacques Derrida.",
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s Kagera Salient was invaded in 1978 by a neighbor. John Okello led an uprising that united the clove-producing Pemba Island with this country, which has been ruled solely by the Chama Cha Mapinduzi Party since independence. The concept of \"Ujamaa\" was promulgated in the Arusha Declaration, which called for African Socialism in this country. For 10 points, identify this East African country led after independence by Julius Nyerere, whose largest city is Dar es Salaam.",
      "answer": "Tanzania"
    },
    {
      "question": "A provisional government led by this man was ended by an 1870 expedition led by Garnet Wolseley, and he later took a seat in parliament despite being an outlaw on the run. This man ordered the execution of Thomas Scott, and was himself was captured and executed for treason by the government of John A. Macdonald following a defeat at the battle of Batoche. For 10 points, name this Metis leader of the Red River and Northwest rebellions in Canada.",
      "answer": "Louis David Riel"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s wedding was preceded by a failed assassination attempt against Gaspard de Coligny, and this ruler gained a decisive victory at the battle of Ivry over the Duke of Mayenne and the Catholic League. This ruler was assassinated by Francois Ravaillac, though he survived the St. Bartholomew’s Day massacre. After repeated failed sieges of Paris, he gained the throne by converting to Catholicism. For 10 points, name this victor of the War of the Three Henries, the first French king from the House of Bourbon.",
        "answer": "Henry IV of France"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry IV issued this edict granting religious tolerance to Huguenots in 1598. It was later overturned by the Edict of Fontainebleau.",
        "answer": "Edict of Nantes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A woman led an uprising against this ruler that culminated in the Battle of the Camel. While praying, this man was mortally wounded by the poisoned sword of a Kharijite assassin. This ruler’s son is the subject of the holiday of Ashura, which celebrates his martyrdom. This successor of Uthman was the final of the four “Rightly Guided” caliphs. For 10 points, name this father of Husayn, the first legitimate caliph according to Shi’a Muslims.",
        "answer": "Ali ibn Abi Taib"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ali’s wife was what daughter of Muhammad, who lends her name to a Shi’a caliphate that ruled Egypt?",
        "answer": "Fatimah"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man supported the mayoral campaign of George Moscone, leading to his appointment as chairman of the San Francisco Housing Committee. People loyal to this man assassinated Congressman Leo Ryan, after which he laced barrels of Flavor-Aid with cyanide. For 10 points, name this leader of the People’s Temple whose followers committed mass suicide in Guyana.",
        "answer": "Jim Jones"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Congressman who died in office was Larry McDonald, who perished after a Soviet fighter pilot shot down this airline’s Flight 007.",
        "answer": "Korean Airlines"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One member of this group drew a map of the world while in the service of the Wanli Emperor. An influential member of this order is the dedicatee of the Novena of Grace and preached in Goa and Japan. Those two men are Matteo Ricci and Frances Xavier. The founder of this order was wounded at the Siege of Pamplona and wrote The Spiritual Exercises. For 10 points, name this religious order founded by Ignatius of Loyola.",
        "answer": "Jesuits"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Jesuits hosted the Guarani and other indigenous tribes on what settlements in South America?",
        "answer": "Jesuit Reductions"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In October 2014, the city of Derna in this country was occupied by militant members of ISIS. The losing side in the elections of 2014 in this country rejected the results, beginning its second civil war in three years. As a result, the elected government of this country was forced to flee to Tobruk from its capital of Tripoli. For 10 points, name this North African state that was ruled by Muammar al-Gaddafi.",
        "answer": "Libya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gaddafi outlined his political philosophy in this Mao Zedong-inspired book, which was supposed to be required reading for all Libyans.",
        "answer": "The Green Book"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Like Hassler Whitney, this man’s work in algebraic geometry produced a namesake embedding theorem. This man lends his name to situations where no agent is better off if they are the only one to change their strategy. With Harsanyi and Selten, this mathematician won the 1994 Econ Nobel for his work in game theory. For 10 points, identify this schizophrenic subject of the movie A Beautiful Mind.",
        "answer": "John Forbes Nash, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In some games, Nash equilibria can occur when the strategies are of what impure type, in which a player plays each move with a certain probability?",
        "answer": "mixed strategies"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was briefly led by Robert Courtenay. The Treaty of Viterbo ended a period in which this city was controlled by the Latin Empire. The city of Zara was attacked prior to this city in a campaign led by Enrico Dandolo. For 10 points, name this home of the Golden Horn, a city sacked during the Fourth Crusade that was the the capital city of the Byzantine Empire.",
        "answer": "Constantinople"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Enrico Dandolo hailed from Venice, which fought the War of Chioggia with what rival Italian port city, the home of Andrea Dorea?",
        "answer": "Genoa"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "HITLER INVADES RUSSIA",
      "prompt": "During Hitler’s invasion of the Soviet Union, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the German code name for the invasion?",
          "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the year the invasion was launched?",
          "answer": "1941"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the 1939 non-aggression pact that Hitler broke by invading the USSR?",
          "answer": "Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city in southern Russia where an entire German army was forced to surrender in 1943?",
          "answer": "Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the former Russian capital that survived a 900-day siege by German forces?",
          "answer": "Leningrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Soviet Field Marshal who commanded the counter-attack against Germany?",
          "answer": "Georgy Zhukov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a 1943 Soviet victory remembered as the largest tank battle in history?",
          "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became the first German Field Marshal in history to surrender, after being surrounded by Soviet forces during Operation Uranus?",
          "answer": "Friedrich von Paulus SUPREME COURT IN THE 20 TH"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CENTURY",
      "prompt": "Which Supreme Court case…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Desegregated public schools?",
          "answer": "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created a fundamental right to an abortion?",
          "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruled banning interracial marriage unconstitutional?",
          "answer": "Loving v. Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Upheld the internment of Japanese-Americans?",
          "answer": "Korematsu v. United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created a right to privacy?",
          "answer": "Griswold v. Connecticut"
        },
        {
          "question": "Upheld parental notification but struck down spousal notification laws for abortion in 1992?",
          "answer": "Planned Parenthood v. Casey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Excluded illegally obtained evidence from trials?",
          "answer": "Mapp v. Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Guaranteed “liberty of contract” against state regulation and involved bakers’ working hours?",
          "answer": "Lochner v. New York"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1968",
      "prompt": "In the year 1968, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the President of the United States who did not seek re-election because of the unpopularity of the Vietnam War?",
          "answer": "Lyndon Baines Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was shot after the California Democratic primary in a hotel by Sirhan Sirhan?",
          "answer": "Robert Francis Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the group of protesters controversially arrested and put on trial for their actions at that Democratic National Convention?",
          "answer": "Chicago Seven"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the manned space mission that became the first to orbit the Moon?",
          "answer": "Apollo 8"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the March massacre in which US army soldiers killed over 400 villagers in South Vietnam?",
          "answer": "My Lai massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was city in which Martin Luther King Jr was assassinated?",
          "answer": "Memphis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the European city that saw massive student protests and strikes in May?",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the US Navy ship captured by North Korea, whose crew was held prisoner for 11 months?",
          "answer": "USS Pueblo"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The bull Cum Nimis Absurdum created one of these places that was subject to the flooding of the Tiber. A famous family took its name from the “red shield” hanging above their house in one of these places. The common name for these places derives from the area around a foundry in (20 pts)",
        "Venice. During World War II, Jurgen Stroop burnt one of these places to crush an (10 pts)",
        "uprising of prisoners bound for Treblinka. Residents of these places were often obliged to wear yellow clothing. For 10 points, name these districts to which Jews were confined in medieval Europe."
      ],
      "answer": "Jewish ghettos"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During his years in England, this man published A Treatise on the Improvement of Canal Navigation. His contemporary rivals included Oliver Evans, whose designs were deployed in Western (20 pts)",
        "waters. A protege of Benjamin West, this painter-turned-engineer designed a proto-submarine called the Nautilus that brought him to the attention of his partner (10 pts)",
        "Robert Livingston. He used a design from Boulton and Watt to propel his launch of the Clermont on the Hudson River. For 10 points, identify this American founder of the first successful steamboat venture."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Fulton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One victim of this event lent her name to the nonprofit Rachel’s Challenge. Cassie Bernall allegedly answered “Yes” when she was asked if she believed in God by the perpetrators of this event, who were mistakenly described as members of the (20 pts)",
        "“Trenchcoat Mafia” and who killed themselves in a library. An anti-gun documentary directed by (10 pts)",
        "Michael Moore was titled Bowling for [this event]. For 10 points, name this 1997 event in which Eric Harris and Dylan Klebold killed 12 students and a teacher at a high school in Colorado."
      ],
      "answer": "Columbine High School massacre/shooting/etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This object’s advantages were mitigated after a specimen was found on Akutan in the Aleutian Islands, and the Thach Weave was another countermeasure developed against it. This (20 pts)",
        "vehicle often traveled alongside the G4M “Betty” and was designed to replace the A5M “Claude.” The protagonist of Miyazaki’s The (10 pts)",
        "Wind Rises is most famous for designing this object, which was often launched from ships like the Hiryu and Akagi. For 10 points, identify this Mitsubishi-produced WWII-era Japanese fighter plane."
      ],
      "answer": "Mitsubishi A6M Zero"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A chapter of this book describes the \"inexhaustible entertainment\" of its author's surroundings while hoeing his bean field. A poem by Thomas Carew ends a chapter of this book that includes a meticulous list of its author's (20 pts)",
        "expenditures. This book's author proposes the \"realometer\" in its chapter \"Where I (10 pts)",
        "Lived, and What I Lived For.\" The author of this book stressed \"economy\" and \"self-sufficiency\" while living on the land of his friend Ralph Waldo Emerson. For 10 points, name this memoir written by the transcendentalist Henry David Thoreau."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Walden",
        "or, Life in the Woods"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of this house was troubled by the Tour de Nesle affair and lost the Battle of Golden Spurs. That ruler ordered Jacques de Molay burned at the stake and oversaw the papacy’s move to (20 pts)",
        "Avignon. The Albigensian Crusade occurred during this house's rule. This dynasty’s founder succeeded Louis V, the last (10 pts)",
        "Carolingian king. It included Philip IV and the canonized Louis IX, and it preceded the House of Valois. For 10 points, name this French ruling house founded by a man named Hugh."
      ],
      "answer": "House of Capet"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A photograph from this book depicts three young boys sleeping on a barrel, and it derives its title from a line in Rabelais’ Gargantua and Pantagruel. The then-recent invention of flash photography allowed this book’s creator to capture the (20 pts)",
        "poorly-lit places documented in this book, and its last chapter claims that New York’s “tremendous, ever swelling (10 pts)",
        "crowd of wage earners” is “not housed decently.” For 10 points, name this Jacob Riis book that exposed poor living conditions in urban tenements."
      ],
      "answer": "How the Other Half Lives"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this movement supported both the White Feather movement and a universal draft. Earlier, that member of this group aided in the smashing of H.H. (20 pts)",
        "Asquith's windows. This movement organized the Mud March, and was targeted by the Cat and Mouse Acts. This movement accomplished its main goals with the passing of the 1918 (10 pts)",
        "Representation of the People Act and the 1928 Equal Franchise Act. For 10 points, name this movement headed by leaders such as Christabel and Emmeline Pankhurst."
      ],
      "answer": "women’s suffrage movement in the United Kingdom"
    }
  ]
}